[Music]
welcome to embedded I'm Elysia white
alongside Christopher white and today
we're going to talk about space hacking
I guess that's cracking the passwords on
comets and planets to see what's inside
at least I hope so we'll find out I
guess is Arielle Waldman and I'm sure
that she can help us figure it out hey
Arielle thanks for joining us on the
show thanks so much for having me I saw
you speak at the Empire speaker series
the Monterey Bay Aquarium Research
Institute speaker series but for our
listeners who aren't familiar with you
could you tell us about yourself as
though you were on a technical panel if
I was on a technical panel yeah our
listeners are mostly hardware and
software engineers so you know you can
talk science to them big e key yeah so
so for me the most of what I do is focus
on making science more inclusive and
accessible to people from all different
backgrounds to contribute to my work
spends a lot of different projects one
of which is that I am the founder of
space hack org which is a directory of
ways for anyone to participate in space
exploration I am also the global
director of science hack day a weekend
event in which scientists designers and
developers from all over get together to
see what they can prototype in one
weekend and I do a lot of other things
I'm the author of the book what's it
like in space I do a lot of interesting
work traveling around and getting
different science communities started I
was on a National Academy of Sciences
committee about the future of human
spaceflight advising the nation on how
to build a sustainable human spaceflight
program over the next several decades
and I am also the advisor to NASA
innovative advanced concepts which is
NASA's more futuristic sci-fi ask sort
of program that funds kind of out there
ideas that could be transformative to
future space missions so many things
so many questions I know it is and
that's only like a short saying like
everything but ya know I like I like to
do a lot of geeky different things and
your background is as an artist yes yeah
so I started you know working well in
sort of the art world I can I guess I
went to art school and I got my degree
in graphic design so I didn't really do
anything
science or space related until the last
few years and how how have you gotten
into science yeah it was kind of an
unexpected scenario for me so you know I
had I had gone to art school and I was
working at an ad agency and had recently
moved to San Francisco and I was
watching a documentary about NASA one
evening and I thought it was a really
cool documentary because it was
interviewing all the old guys who used
to work in Mission Control and they were
talking about how when they were hired
at NASA they didn't know anything about
spacecrafts or space exploration really
at all and they were having to figure it
out as they went along and so I was
listening to this and thinking to myself
well I don't know anything about space
exploration and I want a job at NASA
that sounds amazing and so I decided
just on a whim to email someone at NASA
that I had never met I just got a hold
of someone's email address at NASA and I
just emailed them and I say it said I
was a huge fan of NASA which was you
know true for all of like a week or so
at that point and I kind of volunteered
myself and I'm very very unexpectedly
ended up getting a job from email they
emailed me back and they sent me a job
description that they had posted that
day and I applied for the job and I
ended up getting a job at NASA and it
completely changed everything too for me
because it really made me realize that
there's not only that it was just
incredible that I even had that
opportunity but that there were a lot of
opportunities like that for people like
me to get involved in space exploration
and I really just set out on a mission
to give other people the same sort of
opportunities I've been afforded to me
or similar things where they value their
existing skill sets and and backgrounds
to be able to contribute to science and
space exploration and valuable ways how
did you learn the science pieces of it
though I mean you speak very eloquently
about the specifics of computer vision
and the biology pieces of it how do you
how do you learn that part I mean for me
I think a lot of it is I really value
embedding myself in different
communities so you know when I moved to
San Francisco I became very embedded in
the tech communities and the tech
startups and so I feel like the majority
of my friends are actually probably
intact not in science and on the science
side of things you know I try to go to
you know synthetic biology workshops or
just get to talk to more biologists you
know I can't say that I you know know
the intricate inner workings of
everything but I do make an effort to
get to know people in these different
disciplines and through getting to know
people then I really have time to
process you know how science works and
how to effectively translate that to
other disciplines either within science
or outside of science so I think a lot
of it is social I think a lot of it is
you know showing up to the places in
which different people work and
socialize and I think that goes that
goes a long way
okay well I actually have more questions
in this vein but we are supposed to be
doing lightning round where we ask you
short questions and we want you to have
short answers and if we are behaving
ourselves which I won't be we won't ask
you why and how and all of the other
things are you ready I guess go for it
what's the coolest satellite coolest
satellite Oh including space probes sure
well I mean I'm just gonna have to go
Voyager one I mean you know it's the
farthest so that's that wasn't easy
enough
definitely close to you what art medium
do you prefer Oh what well I mean I
guess again I'll just go for the easy
answer which is graphic design if it's
considered an art medium which is always
a contentious but you know I really like
graphic styles and I gravitate towards
art that really has I don't know a
communicating function to it although I
know a lot of people would really take
me to task over whether graphic design
is considered art or not but I'll go
with graphic design we consider it a
heart
this may be a dangerous question
favorite astronaut oh okay well well it
is a dangerous question because I mean I
like all of them that I've met so far
but I would definitely pick Anusha am
sorry first private a woman a private
astronaut a woman who went to the
International Space Station who was self
funded also she sponsored the Ansari X
PRIZE which was the competition to build
non-governmental suborbital space
vehicles she does a bunch of really
awesome stuff also she came from Iran to
the United States and I also have some
Iranian heritage so she is awesome for
those reasons but also just genuinely as
a person she is amazing to talk to and
she's perhaps one of the best people to
talk to about the human aspects and the
very human emotions about what it's like
to go into space can you introduce us I
could try favorite fictional spaceship
fictional space oh gosh that one's
difficult uh I don't think I've ever
thought about like ranking them you can
go with least favorite if there's one
that you're like wow that was a stinker
I don't know I don't know I mean for now
I'll just go with you know Star Trek The
Next Generation yeah what's a tip you
think everyone should know
on anything in the world yep oh gosh
okay I'll go with a tip that came from
an astronaut which is if you go into
space make sure you go for longer than
four days because the first four days
your face is really bloated because all
the blood that is usually beneath your
head is actually in like is equalizing
throughout your whole body so your face
is super bloated they call it moon face
it's really uncomfortable and it's not
until about four days later that your
body figures out how to equalize it all
and you feel a lot more comfortable and
a lot less gross so I have been told the
the top tip for going into spaces make
sure you go for longer than four days
all right
I have other Larrin questions but I have
more questions about that so let's just
be done with lightning round
sure and you wrote a book called what's
it like in space and you got to talk to
us lots of astronauts who is the
audience for that book
honestly the audience I know this is
like maybe not the best like pitch for
people but it really was I really tried
to make it for everyone all ages all
genders all you know everywhere
everywhere and everyone I really just
thought it was something that you know
there's a lot of books about space a lot
of them talk about the seriousness of
space and and you know it being this
huge undertaking which it is but I kind
of thought that there should be a book
that goes into the more amusing and
delightful and very human aspects of
space exploration including the
embarrassing ones so so I really just
made it because I had come across all of
these astronauts in my work which was
you know not something everyone gets to
say and I would just keep coming home
with all these really funny stories of
from astronauts about what it was like
in space but they were the stories that
maybe they might not say on stage they
were the stories that they might say
over a cup of coffee or something
yeah no wonder what the stories are that
you get over a couple of beers is heck
um I I enjoyed your book I wish I had
had it many years ago when I wrote an
extraordinarily silly novel about space
travel and wished that I'd had it for
research because one of my research
points was that I found most fascinating
it was about snot of course you did and
and you sort of alluded to this in your
tip everyone should know although it's
good that if I ever get to go to space I
will definitely yeah four days and what
happens to our mucus in zero-g yeah it
essentially just stays there and doesn't
leak out at all so it just feels like
you're always having a stuffy nose and
you always have a cold which also then
means that your sense of taste is pretty
muted as well so yeah it just floats
around in there doesn't come out how did
you how did you manage to talk to the
astronauts without squeeing and being a
fangirl and just going to my god oh my
god
I think sometimes I probably was being a
fangirl but I think that's okay you know
some are some are busier than others and
some some I had met in professional
capacities so it was you know I was able
to to keep my cool because I had to
attend a meeting in addition to meeting
them but I think you know I think it
just really is cool I think it's very
humbling to talk to any of them just
because you know that there's only
around 550 people who have ever been in
space and you know that pretty much
everyone across the entire world wants
to talk to them so you know I try and
keep it short amidst my fangirling is
kind of how I went about it did any of
them try to play it cool like that space
no big deal some of them kind of were
like that and others weren't you know I
think one of the reasons why I really
appreciated interviewing Anousheh Ansari
was because because she wasn't a
governmental astronaut I think she was
really detailed and being able to talk
about you know
embarrassing times and things you know
one thing that I remember is she told to
me that I included in the book was about
how she went to you know she was going
into space she had trained she went to
the International Space Station and you
know when you're in microgravity you
need to zip her up your pockets all the
time otherwise whatever you put in your
pockets will float out and she put a bit
of lipgloss in her pocket and it
accidentally floated out and she
couldn't find it anywhere and of course
the worry when you're in space is
anything floating might hit a button or
might you know ruin something you know
you don't want a bunch of random stuff
floating around in a space station it
could be dangerous and so she looked
everywhere for this you know lipgloss
couldn't find it and she was so
embarrassed she's like oh my god I'm in
space I've trained for this and now I've
probably ruined everything and oh my god
like what is like the main you know
manager going to think of all of this
and she was just too embarrassed to say
and she was just like I've screwed
everything up I've totally ruined
everything and so she finally after I
think a couple days or something Fest up
and they were like oh yeah no big deal
there's like a fam that like sucks up
all the stuff that's floating around is
probably there it acts like a
lost-and-found then she went and it was
there and it was perfectly fine like no
big deal but I really appreciate stories
like that because I feel like the
stories of embarrassment are the things
that at least for me I can relate to a
lot I can I can really relate to you
know going like oh great I'm in space
and now I've totally messed something up
and everyone else here is you know like
doing everything right and I'm the
screw-up or something so I I really you
know I like those mundane but silly
stories about space they make it
approachable yeah and it's nice to make
science approachable yeah it's it's kind
of a tragedy that it isn't more
approachable and it doesn't really make
sense because you know for me I think I
would argue that humans have made it
unapproachable that it is approachable
by design but now
have to kind of dismantle a lot of the
walls that people have put up around it
over the last few decades did you tell
me more about that yeah I mean you know
science is something that really became
properly a professional discipline over
you know the 1900s and you know and with
that came a lot of benefits we were able
to make a lot of amazing discoveries and
peer review is able to make sure that
you know the science that we take in and
listen to and and do is is you know
proper and up to up to standards for the
most part those are positive things the
negative things are that science used to
more center around amateurs around
people who were sort of either self
educated or self funded for the
privileged and you know that had its own
drawbacks and that like a lot of the
amateurs who are doing science were very
privileged individuals typically but the
concept of it being something where you
didn't have to have a very specific in a
very narrow background in order to make
real contributions to it I think is
something that has gotten lost and
something that over the last I would say
you know 10 10 to 15 years people have
been trying to reclaim a bit with the
term citizen science I personally don't
like the phrase citizen science I think
there's a lot bundled into that that
doesn't properly just treat Sciences
science no matter who does it but I
think you know the concept of getting
people from different disciplines at
different backgrounds to contribute
toward a to science and and really
acknowledging their value as they exist
not their value if they drop everything
and get a PhD in science I think is
really important and something where
science as a human endeavor has sort of
lost its way I think right now we're in
this stage where people are still
talking about citizen science as being
this kind of I don't know how else to
put
but cute thing where you know oh people
can make measurements for you and and
that citizen-science yeah it's
frustrating it's a step in the right
direction but we're still not yet at the
era where people can be very
self-directed and that it sort of breaks
out from being citizen science breaks
out from being a top-down sort of thing
which it is very much right now you see
government agencies like the National
Science Foundation and other places talk
about valuing citizen science but they
still don't actually do the work in
changing their systems to make it easier
for individuals without academic
affiliations to actually apply for
grants they don't make it easier for
people to do self-directed work and and
so people like myself have to really
navigate this kind of you know
figuratively with a machete and and
start figuring out how to do the stuff
that we want to do without it being
constrained into a very neat and orderly
little box where we're only allowed to
make you know measurements so there's a
lot I can say about this subject but I
think that is that sort of summarizes it
for me is is you know we're needing to
re-break down the walls but then also
make it something that it's not just for
the privileged few to to do and we need
to really start moving where people who
want to contribute to science who come
from non-traditional backgrounds have
autonomy they don't have to just do work
within a very constrained set of
parameters but they can actually do
self-directed work okay let me see if I
understand what you're saying because I
think there are several important points
here when we went from natural
philosophers to scientists they were
often wealthy and privileged and they
were driven by curiosity and love of
discovery and now as we talk about
amateurs they may still be privileged
and funded or may not be given the
access that
many people in the world have they don't
necessarily have to be doing full-time
science through discovery and curiosity
now they can contribute in other ways
unfortunately the ways that they are
being forced to contribute are in the
small mechanical Turkish citizen science
could be done by a robot if only we
invented that robot sorts of ways yeah I
would say that's like a decent summary
of it and so I think that's where your
space hack
org comes in a little bit I mean space
hacked org was something that I built
ten years ago because I had learned
about a lot of different opportunities
in which people could contribute to the
furthering of space exploration they
were both small endeavors like making
sort of Mechanical Turk like
measurements and also larger ones like
figuring out how to build the next
generation of Mars rovers that work
nothing like any of the existing Rovers
do it was you know and I think I've
certainly evolved more in the last ten
years since space hack I think space
hack really as I was getting a cracked
into the this first era of open science
and citizen science which is there are
cool opportunities to do different
things and if that thing is your GM then
go for it
what space hawk org doesn't have as much
but but has been successful I think and
at least inspiring it has been sort of
making people aware that there are ways
to contribute to space exploration out
there and that you know for a lot of
people it might be a good entry point to
go and try out one of these projects
whether it's you know searching for
black holes or or building you know Mars
rovers what-have-you and I've had good
feedback from people who have started
there and then just started doing their
own self directed stuff so space octo
org really was meant to be something
that is it successful in sort of getting
people to go find something that
delights them and then you know and then
they're just off on their own sort of
just being that
spark for people to realize that they're
valuable to science as they exist today
so I think you know Space Act org was
the start and then I think what was a
couple of years after doing space Hawk
org then started science hack day which
gets people to prototype all sorts of
things and doesn't issue challenges and
doesn't keep people to tidy little boxes
but lets people be self-directed in
their you know discovery and the light
of things in science I have know as I'm
listening to this I'm thinking about my
own biases and I have a pretty
traditional science education and as I
went through that it was you know piling
history of science on top of history of
science until you finally get to
something near where we are in the
contemporary state of physics or
whatever and that sort of credentialism
is in the back of my mind well it's like
well you can't do anything unless you've
gone through all this and built up all
of this you know there's so much physics
or so much biology but it's not really
true I mean there is but you can always
say that there's too much for any one
person to deal with so there's always
places you can you can do make
discoveries that are still out there
that don't require you to have built up
the last 2,000 years of physics before
you can understand it and one of the
example that I was thinking of was was
observational astronomy where there's
tons of people out there with telescopes
looking at binary stars and comets and
discovering comets and even discovering
extrasolar planets and stuff that you
know they're just doing that yeah I mean
for me all of this is not about
replacing people who have dedicated you
know their lives towards the more you
know what is now traditional sort of
career and and pathway into science it's
more about augmenting to me so it's not
about replacing it's not about saying
you know oh you don't need all of that
to make you know these really big
contribution or anything like that it's
more about that science needs help like
you know that if you want to dedicate
your life to becoming a scientist and a
researcher then you should definitely do
that but
it's also that there's a lot of
serendipitous and unexpected things that
can help science both from a process
point of view and from a discovery point
of view that I think science really has
just shut themselves out of and and sort
of said oh we don't need any help you
yeah you need this many years before we
can even talk to you and that's the part
that has just made me a bit sad because
I have been witness over the last few
years of many many many instances where
scientists and researchers just end up
realizing oh like you know I do
theoretical particle physics I didn't
think I could talk to anyone else about
what I do because you need to know so
much but now I see you know learning
design or learning how to prototype
stuff in electronics or you know getting
learning from other people in different
disciplines I see now how that can
benefit my work and how that can help
and so it's not always about the big win
of like I've discovered an entirely new
you know black hole or planet and in our
galaxy or anything like that sometimes
it's just about process and about
allowing more creative ways of doing
things that sometimes can be really
helpful and I think a lot of scientists
and researchers know this but maybe
haven't fully evaluated it because in
science you're always looking to
repurpose stuff for your own needs
because you need all this specialty
equipment so a lot of times you know you
might be searching Amazon for something
that's used for pets but it's going to
be really useful in your lab because
it's exactly the right size that you
need or the right weight that you need
so you know I witness all the time
scientists and researchers having to be
very creative and and sort of have a
hacker sort of angle to what they do
because it's so often requires specialty
goods and materials and so I think it's
just expanding it a bit to allow people
from you know from the tech era tech
scene from the you know the art scene
and from these different industries and
discipline
to be able to you know have something to
say and allow more creativity to be in
science so to me I really see this as
yeah science will only get better and
and have more unexpected sort of stuff
in it that otherwise wouldn't exist if
it stayed very narrowly focused on only
people who have PhDs in a very specific
discipline it's a hard balance though I
had lunch not too long ago with a friend
that I haven't seen in a while but we
worked together for many years and we
are now after 15 years of not working
together we are starting a new project
and there were so many things I didn't
have to say because there was the common
shared understanding of what we had
already done and that's a lot of getting
a science degree and at pH DS is
creating that thousands of years of of
building up so that you can build a
shared language and I guess for my for
my perspective which is I have a
bachelor's degree in it so you know I
have decent science but not I'm not a
PhD I don't know how to talk to them and
and I get lost I I've been you know I've
been studying robotics for years I'm
sure I could go back on the podcast and
figure out when I fell in love with
Patrick polarski's artificially
intelligent prosthetic limb but how do I
it seems like the Gulf is really far I
see what you want to do but I don't I
don't feel like I don't qualified and if
I'm not qualified how is anybody else
who doesn't have a PhD oh yeah I mean so
so first you know you're talking about
the camaraderie that comes with people
having your shared knowledge and that's
definitely a thing because even me now
being in the space sector for 10 years I
have that with other people where I can
where I don't have
to worry about spelling out
abbreviations or anything uh some basic
stuff you know that's not going anywhere
no one's taking that away from you but I
think there needs to be some sort of an
acknowledgement of the fact that you're
working on yeah thousands or hundreds of
years of you know built up knowledge in
your sector there are other people who
have hundreds of years of knowledge in
their sector and wouldn't it be kind of
sad to say well I'm not going to learn
anything about you know the hundreds of
years of what we know about design and
the effects that it has on people and
the effects that it has on the ability
to get work done because I want to stay
in my vertical you know I think I
understand that it can be difficult to
talk to people in in different verticals
and different areas but I think that's
kind of what's needed I think it's
really sad to allow I guess the pressure
that is put on on researchers to stay
sort of in your in their sector because
of the comfort zone I think people do
need to be thinking about you know well
you know if it's a bit uncomfortable for
me to talk to you know someone else
because I don't have all this shared
stuff and I don't even know where to
begin with them and like where can we
possibly go from here I think it's
important to acknowledge that and to
acknowledge that that maybe that's kind
of a problem not that you need to be
able to have everyone understand your
hundreds of years of knowledge just that
they have their own hundreds of years of
knowledge that you should tap into and
that you know maybe you're not going to
understand everything about each other
at the end of the day but if you can get
some insights from one another then it's
really useful and you know we see this
happen between scientific disciplines
all the time where it's like oh my god
we are now using this technique from
biology but we're applying it towards
robotics and you know we're building
soft robotics because it's working based
on stuff that we've learned
about biology stuff like that happens
all the time does it mean that the robot
assist is like really really
knowledgeable about everything about
biology no but they've got some little
kernel that is actually going to really
benefit their work and also I think it
builds better connections to know that a
roboticist could ask a biologist about
you know how something works and that
you know there can be enough
communication to really make a benefit
on both sides so I don't think it's
about figuring out how to embed your
your brain into someone else's brain but
but it's about what can those kernels be
and and knowing that you can ask people
and that it's okay and that if they
struggle a little bit to tell you like
how this all works but that's okay it's
okay to be a bit uncomfortable but to
not try means that we are kind of you
we're kind of just giving up a whole ton
of possibilities that we'll never know
what was possible because we're not even
trying
alright I totally understand and know
that I understand that you are looking
more for an interdisciplinary approach
in a more communicative and appreciating
the diversity of mind and knowledge that
other people have yeah okay I totally
make sense I totally make sense okay
yeah
not then I didn't but if that don't make
sense I mean and so now I feel like
we've we've really crossed over into
science hack day because I think this is
part of what it is yeah where you're
you're getting these people in the same
room and then you're saying okay let's
play yeah yeah it's totally that and I
have to say you know scientists and
researchers coming into science Hawk day
have been the most skeptical for sure
but a hundred percent across the board
once they've actually come to the
weekend and and worked on prototyping
things with people from different
disciplines they come out the other side
and they're like I get it now I get it I
get how this is like beneficial both to
me and my work but all
so to other people and it's it's been
really a heartwarming project perhaps I
would I would say it's the most
heartwarming project of all the work
I've done over my many years know on on
earth my many short years I guess
depending on how many which way you look
at it but uh but yeah I so you know it's
something where we leave it really
open-ended it's kind of like organized
chaos in a good way
it's it's something where people can
decide what they want to do so if you're
coming in and you're saying I want to
stick to my comfort zone but I want to
have you know a team of whoever is
interested work on stuff in my comfort
zone you can do that but you can also
come in and be like you know I've always
been fascinated by jellyfish and I've
never had the chance or permission to
like just do stuff with jellyfish even
though I know nothing about them you
know it's that sort of safe playground
where you can do these sorts of things
and I think pretty much across the board
everyone comes into it a bit uncertain a
bit of like I don't know what I have to
contribute or I don't know how I'm going
to relate to anyone and everyone comes
out the other side you know having sort
of created an experience that is
life-changing either on a very minuscule
scale or life-changing on a large scale
on the miniscule scale it's that stuff
that I was talking about of just
creating sort of a mental locket where
you know that you can play around with
stuff that you know nothing about and
that that's okay and that if you just
did it for one weekend and you never do
it again but you know that it's always
available to you then that's the only
change that I want to do whether you're
a scientist who wants to know that you
could play around in another science
discipline you've never touched or
you're someone with an art degree who
wants to know that you can play around
with space data and that's something
that's okay to do so it's not
necessarily about building expertise
it's about building accessibility
with everyone's individual brain so to
speak the knowledge that this stuff is
available to you and and that it's okay
to play around with things if you don't
know why you're doing it and if you
don't know where it's going or any of
that unfortunately I think a lot of
people need that permission to be able
to feel like they can do stuff outside
of where they exist and I think just
having that permission to do that I
think is enough of a change that if it
happened on a large scale I think I
think all disciplines would be having a
lot more creative approaches in them and
things that otherwise what we might be
giving up yes yes but are there actually
jellyfish we have had jellyfish
biologists at science act day for sure I
don't think we've had an actual
jellyfish we've had pig hearts we've had
weird things we've had ants that were
controlled through vibration we've had
some some odd stuff for sure but I don't
think anyone has brought a jellyfish to
science hack day yet maybe we should
back up and actually say it's a weekend
long event and there are some coming up
there is one in India in mid-october or
one in San Francisco in late October and
one in France in late November yes and I
believe there's perhaps one coming up in
Colombia too that will be posted on the
website shortly and so these are two or
three-day events do you get do people
get invited to people just apply how do
it does it cost to attend how does all
of that work yeah so it's entirely free
to attend events it's volunteer run it's
something where we open up the
registration for anyone to attend you
don't have to be you know it's not an
application process like anyone can sign
up to it
some people do get invites just because
in my experience there's a lot of
awesome people who we'd like to have at
these events and individual invites go a
long way to telling people that we
really care about having them there and
that they are valuable so it's kind of
both an open registration and we send
out invites to two people and both ways
are successful so it's something where
yeah anyone attends and what we try and
do on sort of the back end of everything
is just make sure that we've got a good
balance between you know technologists
and and art people and scientists and
and people from many other disciplines
so as people sign up we try and look at
you know what general occupations people
might be might be when they're
registering and if we're like oh we've
got a lot of web developers and not
enough artists or something then we'll
tailor our outreach to target more
artists so the important thing with it
is really just trying to make sure that
we do have a good balance of people with
different backgrounds at the event and
from there we open it up so you know
people come on a Saturday morning we
have lightning talks so and those
lightning talks are about a bunch of
different disciplines just kind of open
science stuff that people can play
around with so open data sets or open
visualization tools and really the
lightning talks are just there to help
people on a Saturday morning because
everyone's coming in a bit fuzzy fuzzy
brained and you know might need some
things to react to to think about like
what they may or may not want to work on
but after the Lightning talks we really
just encourage people to eavesdrop on
each other's conversations talk to each
other if it takes them several hours to
figure out what they want to do that's
fine but really you know for for these
science hack days we give them 24
consecutive hours to make anything they
want that is related to science
people come up with some pretty
wackadoodle things some people work on
some very serious problem solving it's
really open to anyone and people can be
part of multiple teams they can be a
part of one team in a way science acting
is not only sort of breaking down
barriers with science I anticipate bonds
had become very competitive spaces where
you need very technical skill sets and
again as being someone who's not from
that discipline I found that really
frustrating because I think a lot of
people have the desire to want to figure
out how to prototype something if even
if they have no idea how to and so
science hack day really tries to leave
everything open-ended so that you get
all of these wonderful unexpected
collisions between people and between
ideas and between different ways of
prototyping things but you kept the 24
hour the overnight from from hackathons
though that's always been my kryptonite
yeah I'm sorry I have to sleep that's
where all my ideas come and yeah and you
and you can sleep so you know you don't
have to stay up all overnight you know I
think we kept the weekend event because
humans unfortunately well not
unfortunately humans realistically you
know they have a set amount of time
where they can get really excited about
something and put a lot into it and then
they're like I am tired I need to go to
sleep so we keep the overnight part of
it you know some people stay up all
night I would say the majority go home
and get sleep and come back the next
morning and keep going so that part is
you know optional you don't have to stay
up all all night working on something
but you know some people that's how they
work and and so leaving it open-ended so
that multiple different pathways can be
successful still I think is the
important part and you don't have prizes
but you do have sponsors yeah so we have
sponsors who pay for all the food and
help pay for different aspects of the
event but they don't pay for prizes they
don't get to
shape the event we you know they provide
the necessary you know venue and and
food and everything but in terms of
prizes we still offer things like you
know best design best use of data stuff
like that but we award medals that say
science on them and then we have a medal
award ceremony and it's just a lot of
fun and I think by not having big prizes
it makes it a lot more collaborative
people tend to be less secretive and
it's really just about fun and so even
with the prize categories of these
medals we have some that are thought of
beforehand like yeah best hardware best
use of data stuff like that but each
year we tell the judges to invent
categories based on what they've seen so
it's really just kind of fun and on the
fly and you know we had one year I think
where it was like best whale hack or
something because someone had made a
really cool net with like LEDs on it
that would deter whales from getting
tangled into it and you know so so like
the event itself we try and keep that
aspect pretty open-ended and and broad
and how do you find people to attend do
you how do you publicize event yeah
a lot of it so each city each city has
their own organizer so science hack day
isn't a franchise it's not an
organization anyone can organize a
science hack day in their city there's
instructions on the website for how to
do that and so each city I think
publicizes it a bit differently based on
the knowledge of their own community in
San Francisco we've done it a lot by
word-of-mouth but I try and make it
diverse by default even though it's
word-of-mouth by recruiting people from
different disciplines and areas into the
organizing team so for instance the very
first year that we did science hack day
I had I did it a bit overkill I had 15
people on the organizing committee which
was
definitely definitely too many I learned
my lesson from that but but one of the
things I remember from that first year
was oh like there's a whole you know
biotech scene in San Francisco and we
want to make sure like that they come to
the event well the best thing we thought
of to do that year was I just pretty
much reached out to someone in biotech
someone that I didn't know previously
and I just said do you want to be part
of the science acting organizing
committee and they agreed and because of
having that person who's already
embedded in those communities on the
organizing committee it sort of meant
that when we were doing word-of-mouth
that we were making sure to reach out
into the biotech community as much as
other things so it's again it's not
trying to sort of replace anyone and say
I can figure it out on my own it's
acknowledging oh okay so I know people
in these communities what are the other
communities in the local area that we
want to make sure that we reach out to
and not overlook and then recruiting
your organizing committee based on that
means that I think you have a lot more
authentic word of mouth outreach and you
can do a better job of sort of breaking
out of your own little eco chambers so I
put a lot of effort at the start on the
organizing committee and the makeup of
that organizing committee and then kind
of go from there so so that's that's one
way it's not the only way but that's
been a really important part because
otherwise you have a bunch of people who
you know are like we know we need to
reach out to these other communities but
we don't know anyone there well let's
just you know force it and there's like
it doesn't usually work that way you
usually want people from the communities
that you're speaking to to actually be
involved in the process very much so
that makes sense so moving away from
that what is up next for you yeah so I
have a couple of things happening this
year this year is my big exploration
here I would say so in just about two
weeks I am going aboard the exploration
vessel Nautilus to explore
an underwater volcano that is an
analogue to Enceladus the moon of Saturn
that is an icy moon that has ocean
beneath the ice and has likely
hydrothermal activity on it so we're
going to be going to this underwater
volcano to better understand the extreme
forms of life that might live around it
so that we can better understand what
extreme forms of life might live on
Enceladus the other expedition that I'm
doing this year is I am going to
Antarctica for a month to do video
microscopy of all of the extremophiles
and extreme microorganisms that live
beneath the ice in a number of different
locations in Antarctica and actually
trying to just get more video of how
they interact and what they look like
and and how they move around and just
better understand kind of the microbial
Serengeti so to speak that exists in
Antarctica and making people aware that
there's actually a lot of life in this
otherwise barren landscape those are
very connected yes yeah I'm very cold
and one very hot yes yeah yeah both of
them are about you know astrobiology so
you know the sort of multidisciplinary
discipline of understanding extreme
forms of life here on earth so that we
can better understand how life might
exist elsewhere in our solar system
and in our galaxy and in the universe
generally and so it's you your plan is
video microscopy so we'll be able to see
little things battling it out or eating
each other or whatever it is they do yes
building tiny cities torture yeah
and then are you making a movie so I'll
be taking a bunch of videos all of the
videos and photos that I take in
Antarctica I'm going to put under
Creative Commons license
but I will be after I get back from
Antarctica I will be sort of stitching
together all of these videos and putting
it into an interactive website that's
going to give people sort of the the
feeling
of what it's like to actually just look
down the barrel of a microscope while
you're in Antartica and the stuff that
you can find so being able to just sort
of pan around and zoom in and sort of
get more of a sense of what all of these
things are and and how they interact in
their environments is kind of the goal
was this your first set of research
expeditions or is this old hat for you
this is these are my first I I hope they
are the first of money I hope I hope to
be doing much more but yeah these these
I have never been on a research vessel
before I've never been to Antarctica
before I do travel a lot but it's not
always science driven these these two
are both definitely science driven so I
hope it's the first of a hopefully a
long career and doing more exploratory
stuff like this I'm lost in thinking
back to the looking at the microbes and
I want it to be VR and I want to be a
microbe I want to play a game about
being a microbe I know that that's a
game I yeah sorry you keep saying all
these amazing things and I just like
tally fish talking and I'm not supposed
to interrupt but jellyfish a jellyfish
are pretty badass I mean I said I was
you know when I was at and barri
I was talking to Connie and blinking on
her last name but Connie um she is this
amazing you know marine kind of marine
roboticist is the way I'd almost
describe her she does all this amazing
stuff about bio-inspired design and she
was talking about creating sort of
jellyfish inspired robots which of
course yeah hey I think everyone on this
on this podcast right now Lloyd agree is
like pretty frickin amazing to think
about so yeah yeah there's cool stuff
with jellyfish for sure and you know if
you're super you know fancy about it
they're just jellies they're not
jellyfish but but there will always be
jellyfish to me okay one more area of
things I want to ask you about and that
is an IAC yeah nyuk-nyuk which is NASA
innovative advanced concepts which I
mean that sounds like it's the warp
drive people yeah
that is the workshare people okay the
people who are doing advanced concepts
for NASA
wait that's kind of in the name wasn't
it yes yeah what is that and what do you
do for them yeah so Nayak is a program
that funds
futuristic sci-fi inspired sometimes out
there ideas that could be transformative
to future space missions 20 30 40 years
down the line things that maybe aren't
possible yet today but you could still
do incredible research into if they're
liable or not and so it's this
incredible program the sort of things
that they fund or things like using
comments as propulsion systems or using
glitter as in Space Telescope's weird
stuff you know stuff that definitely is
straddling the you know out there stuff
they are not the warp drive people
because I work drive stuff I think has
been an entirely separate thing because
they are looking at stuff from a
credible perspective so they have funded
things that are like looking into like
fusion powered propulsion systems which
fusion is still something that hasn't
fully materialized yet but but you can
still do a lot of credible stuff looking
into it today but yeah they I think it's
a really amazing program because anyone
can apply so you can be a garage hacker
you can you can be an academic you can
already work within NASA it's open to
any US citizens to apply if you're not a
US citizen as long as you partner with
a u.s. institution you can also apply
and I think it's it's really great and I
think this is my personal opinion it's
it's the most successful when it's
pulling from people who maybe
aren't directly in the space industry so
you know people who maybe are coming at
it from a biological perspective or
human physiology perspective or
something and maybe you know maybe
working in the space industry is not
their full-time job there's also very
successful things that come from within
NASA because it's a great opportunity
for people within NASA who have really
great ideas but might not have a boss
who's very supportive of it or might not
have any funding mechanisms for they're
a great idea to have a sort of a home so
Nyack has an external council of people
who advise it sort of from the outside
these are sci-fi authors and quantum
physicists and people of different
disciplines so I am one of the people on
that external council and we try to help
Nayak maintain that delicate balance
between science and science fiction we
don't want things that are too far into
science fiction and we don't want things
that are too safe so we try to keep the
program balanced I don't get to actually
review any of the proposals that come in
which is actually a positive thing
because then I can encourage people to
apply and I don't have to worry about
any conflicts there but we try to sort
of take a step back and look at the
overall program and advise it on that
basis so right now the solicitation to
apply to Nayak is open and I think it
closes in mid-september and all that's
needed to initially apply to Nayak is a
three-page white paper so it's a it's a
pretty incredible program and I'm
totally totally biased in saying this
but it's my favorite NASA program so it
can't be a three page white paper about
anything there were specific areas like
there's some data from Cassini tell us
what you want to do with it or did I not
understand no no there's not specific
areas not for Nayak it just needs to be
within a mission context so a lot of the
important stuff that you got evaluated
on
is about it being in a mission context
and that can be a mission that is either
currently being talked about something
like your you know NASA I going to
Europa or it can be just plausible so it
can be stuff in cosmology it can be
stuff in in human life support it can be
you know planetary stuff so there's been
you know funded concepts that are about
you know orbiting Pluto there have been
ones about you know studying dark energy
so it could be really about anything as
long as it seems that it's plausible
that it could be a NASA mission and this
also includes Aeronautics as well
alright then apparently I was looking at
the wrong website but I will have the
right website in the show nuts so maybe
other people will look yeah it's it
should just be NASA at nasa.gov slash
Nyack okay ah let's see what is the
future of human spaceflight
in lightning Rapids which should have
been a short answer right okay well yeah
it's a long answer oh my gosh yeah where
do you want me to begin with that
propulsion Oh
propulsion well I mean propulsion is I
mean so I'll back up and say you know
space exploration is something that is
really interesting about the perception
of it within people who really work on
it as as their full-time thing and and
sort of people outside of that because I
think the tendency for a lot of people
is to view space exploration as being
this exponential thing similar to what
we've seen in parts of biology where
it's just like every year we're able to
like process more and do more and it's
just this exponential like through the
roof sort of chart space exploration a
lot of people perceive it to be that way
but it's really really not space
exploration pretty much the model of it
is you know have a breakthrough and then
spend years and decades optimizing that
breakthrough but pretty much be at the
same
until another breakthrough comes along
and this is actually you know what Nayak
is really around is Nayak sort of
understands that space exploration
requires breakthroughs to be
transformative it's not an exponential
thing we're still using chemical rockets
and until another breakthrough comes
along and we get you know some other
type of propulsion that really changes
the game then all we're doing all that
any innovative rocket company is doing
is just optimizing the hell out of
chemical rockets and there are
optimizations to have like you know the
fact that we're finally getting reusable
rockets and stuff like that and that's
cool but until yeah until a big
breakthrough comes along then we're more
or less stuck with sort of the same
state of stuff so the future of human
spaceflight is something where the
report that I worked on and looked at
both present-day technology and what we
called foreseeable technology so things
that don't exist but it's pretty
foreseeable in our current state of
everything to imagine people figuring
out so an example is landing humans on
the surface of Mars right now no one has
built whatever it is going to be that
safely lands humans on the surface of
Mars we can't use any of the stuff that
we've been using to land robots on Mars
because that would kill squishy humans
this is we have to invent new stuff that
doesn't exist right now
no-one's built it but it's within the
realm of foreseeable technology we felt
that you know stuff like that
it doesn't exist but it can probably be
done it most likely can be done but at
the start of the report we pretty much
acknowledged that because space
exploration depends on breakthroughs
that you know if a huge breakthrough in
technology happen and so we got you know
fusion powered Rockets or something like
that then then it rewrites the whole
game and that's kind of how space has
worked from from the get-go is you know
something comes along oftentimes from a
completely different sector and it just
completely changes the game
you know ballistic missiles changed the
game and and so that's kind of how space
works and so you know the report about
the future of human spaceflight looked
at as much as we could present day and
foreseeable technologies and evaluated
it based off of those but we also
acknowledge that breakthroughs can and
do happen they don't seem to happen that
often but when they do it rewrites
everything yeah okay well Christopher do
you have any questions you want to ask
Ariel
well we could talk for a few more hours
yeah that's the problem yeah we should
probably let her go maybe maybe I'll
come back and tell us about microbes yes
yeah yeah once I once I get back from my
two expeditions I imagine I'll have a
lot more insights to share an advice for
being on large boats for long times oh
my god yeah I just tried my prescription
motion sickness patch so I'm preparin to
I'm preparing for that experience it'll
be so cool Ariel do you have any
thoughts you'd like to leave us with uh
I mean not anything in particular we've
we've covered a lot of ground I always
have more to share I think you know just
just that you can follow along on my
expeditions to nautilus and Antarctica
on my patreon page and also I have a
YouTube channel where I will be trying
to share as much as I can from those
expeditions and and everything so that's
probably going to be the two places you
can easily find me all right I'll make
sure those are in the show notes our
guest has been Ariel Waldman co-author
of a congressionally requested National
Academy of Sciences report on the future
of human spaceflight
she's the author of the book what's it
like in space stories from astronauts
who've been there and Ariel sits on the
council for the NASA innovative advanced
concepts
something advanced program program
program she is finally the director of
science hack day she's got a lot more
titles clearly we could have gone for a
lot longer but thank you for being with
this area yeah thank you so much for
having me this is fun check out these
show notes
in your podcast app or on HTTP slash
slash embedded fm put a colon in there
too somewhere I don't know thank you to
Christopher for producing and co-hosting
and of course thank you for listening
you can always contact us directly at
show at embedded FM or hit the contact
link on that HTTP colon slash slash
embedded fm finally from me a quote and
leave you with one of my favorite
scientists Mary Curie nothing in life is
to be feared it is only to be understood
now is the time to understand more so
that we may fear less emitted is an
independently produced radio show that
focuses on the many aspects of
Engineering it is a production of
logical elegance and embedded software
consulting company in California if
there are advertisements in the show we
did not put them there and do not
receive money from them at this time our
sponsors are logical elegance and
listeners like you